A Guide to the Deeds of easement of the Virginia Dept. of Historic Resources, 1969-2010
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Deeds of easement of the Virginia Dept. of Historic Resources, 1969-2010
The Library of Virginia
29886, 29907, 30155, 30409, 30654, 30802, 30973, 31008, 32920, 33628, 34981, 35101, 35180, 35187, 35188, 35680, 37305, 39119, 41222, 42473, 43430, 44477, 45052, 45157
4.5 cu. ft. (10 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the State Archivist, Library of Virginia, 31 August 2009.
Biographical Information
The Dept. of Historic Resources was created by an act of the General Assembly passed on March 27, 1989 in order to encourage, stimulate, and support the identification, evaluation, protection, preservation, and rehabilitation of the Commonwealth's significant historic, architectural, archaeological and cultural resources; to establish and maintain a permanent record of those resources; and to foster a greater appreciation of these resources among the citizen's of Virginia. In order to carry out these objectives the department administers a variety of programs, including a statewide survey of historic buildings, districts and archaeological sites; administration the Virginia Landmarks Register and participation in the National Register of Historic Places; the Highway Historical Markers program and the Preservation Easement program. The department also maintains an archives of historic sites, conducts environment reviews, provides markers for historical sites, publishes and conducts workshops for public education and coordinates historical preservation efforts among individuals, groups and governments and provides archaeological and technical assistance to these entities. The director is appointed by the governor and serves as the State Historic Preservation Officer for the purpose of carrying out the National Historic Preservation Act of 1966.
The Dept. of Historic Resources traces its roots back to the Division of History and the Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission. The Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission was created by an act of the General Assembly passed on April 6, 1966, to establish, designate, preserve, and mark historical landmarks. The Division of History was created within the State Commission on Conservation and Development in 1929. In 1938 the General Assembly approved the renaming of the State Commission on Conservation and Development to the Virginia Conservation Commission. The name was changed once again to the Dept. of Conservation and Development as a result of the state reorganization act approved by the General Assembly in 1948, and in 1958 became the Dept. of Conservation and Economic Development. In 1985, the Department of Conservation and Historic Resources and a separate Dept. of Economic Development were created. Also in 1985, The Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission staff became the Division of Historic Landmarks within newly created Dept. of Conservation and Historic Resources. The Dept. of Historic Resources was created in 1989 when the Division of Historic Landmarks, (previously the Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission, created in 1966), split off from the Dept. of Conservation and Historic Resources and became its own agency.
Scope and Content
This series contains original deeds of easement for historic buildings and sites in Virginia. Starting in 2008, some deed files also include Baseline Documentation Reports. These reports describe the character and condition of the property being placed under the historic preservation easement and the public benefit of the conservation. The reports include statement of value; building structure and site description; conservation purpose; notes, photographs, maps and national register nomination form.
Contents List
- Aberdeen Gardens Historic District - 57 Mary Peake Boulevard, Hampton (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- Academy of Music, Lynchburg (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- Accomack County Courthouse, Accomack County (Acc. 41222), 1999 (Box 1)
- Alexander Baker Historic District, Winchester (Acc. 45157), 1992 (Box 1)
- Alexandria Academy, Alexandria (Acc. 35680), 1997 (Box 1)
- Allmand-Archer House, Norfolk (Acc. 30155), 1977; 1986 (Box 1)
- Ampthill, Cumberland County (Acc. 42473), 2005 (Box 1)
- Anderson House (William Anderson House - 302 Lee Lane, Fincastle), Botetourt County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- Attucks Theater, Norfolk (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- Avenell, Bedford City (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- B. Williams and Co. Store, Mathews County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Nov 18 (Box 10)
- Baird Tract - Ream's Station Battlefield, Dinwiddie County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Dec 15 (Box 9)
- Balch Library (Thomas Balch Library), Leesburg, Loudoun County (Acc. 39119), 2000 (Box 1)
- Bank of the Potomac, Alexandria (Acc. 33628), 1987 (Box 1)
- Barnes House, Stafford County (Acc. 44477), 2007 Aug 21 (Box 9)
- Barret House, Richmond City (Acc. 29886), 1975 (Box 1)
- Battersea, Petersburg (Acc. 44477), 2008 May 6 (Box 9)
- Bayne-Fowle House, Alexandria (Acc. 45157), 1986 (Box 1)
- Bayville Farm, Virginia Beach (Acc. 35680), 1993 (Box 1)
- Beacon Theater, Hopewell (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 1)
- Bear Mountain Indian School, Amherst County (Acc. 41222), 2004 (Box 1)
- Beaumont - Madison Barbour Historic District, Orange County (Acc. 35680 and 43430), 1996; 2001 (Box 1)
- Beauregard Farm - Brandy Station Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 45052), 2010 June 9 (Box 10)
- Bedford City/County Museum, Bedord City (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- Bedford Historic District - 124 S. Bridge St., Bedford City (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 1)
- Bedford Historic Meeting House, Bedford City Acc. 35680), 1996 (Box 1)
- Bel Air, Prince William County (Acc. 33628), 1988 (Box 1)
- Belgian Building, Richmond City (Acc. 45052), 2010 Mar 16 (Box 10)
- Ben Lomond, Prince William County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- Bentfield, Brunswick County (Acc. 29886), 1973 (Box 1)
- Berkeley, Charles City County (Acc. 29886 and 31008), 1975; 1980 (Box 1)
- Berry Hill, Halifax County (Acc. 39119), 1991; 1992; 1993; 2001 (Box 1)
- Black House (Justice Hugo Black House), Alexandria (Acc. 29886), 1969 (Box 1)
- Blenheim, Westmoreland County (Acc. 29886), 1976 (Box 1)
- Blenheim, Campbell County (Acc. 45157), 1993 (Box 1)
- Bly Farm - Fisher's Hill Battlefield, Shenandoah County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Dec 4 (Box 10)
- Bogota House Tract, Rockingham County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Nov 17 (Box 10)
- Boykin's Tavern, Isle of Wight County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 1)
- Braehead, Fredericksburg (Acc. 44477), 2007 Dec 10 (Box 9)
- Branch House, Richmond City (Acc. 35187), 1982 (Box 1)
- Breakthrough Battlefield, Petersburg and Dinwiddie County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 1)
- Breckenridge Mill, Botetourt County (Acc. 39119), 2000 (Box 1)
- Bremo Historic District - Upper Bremo, Fluvanna County (Acc. 31008), 1980; 2006 (Box 1)
- Brentmoor - Spillman-Mosby House, Warrenton, Fauquier County (Acc. 39119), 2000 (Box 1)
- Brentsville Courthouse, Prince William County (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 1)
- Brickley House, Prince William County (Acc. 45157), 1990 (Box 1)
- Brill Property - Fisher's Hill Battlefield, Shenandoah County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Dec 2 (Box 9)
- Bristoe Station Battlefield Heritage Park, Prince William County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Oct 20 (Box 10)
- Brooke's Bank, Essex County (Acc. 29886), 1971 (Box 1)
- Bruce House (T. Seddon Bruce House) - 207 W. Franklin St., Richmond City (Acc. 29886), 1977 (Box 1)
- Buckland Tavern - Buckland Historic District, Prince William County (Acc. 45052), 2009 July 29 (Box 10)
- Bumgardner Tract - Appomattox Court House Battlefield, Appomattox County (Acc. 44477), 2009 Mar 5 (Box 9)
- Burgh Westra, Gloucester County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 1)
- Burks-Guy-Hagan House, Bedford County (Acc. 35187), 1985 (Box 1)
- Burlington, King William County (Acc. 29886 and 35680), 1977; 1996 (Box 1)
- Burlington, Orange County (Acc. 35101 and 35680), 1996 (Box 1)
- Bush Meeting Tabernacle at Fireman's Field, Loudoun County (Acc. 44477), 2008 May 1 (Box 9)
- Butler Tract - Deep Bottom I Battlefield, Henrico County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Oct 8 (Box 10)
- Cactus Hill Archaeological Site, Sussex County (Acc. 41222), 2001 (Box 2)
- Caleb Rector House, Fauquier County (Acc. 45052), 2010 Mar 12 (Box 10)
- Camden Farm, Caroline County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Oct 10 (Box 9)
- Camp Family Homestead - Franklin Historic District, Franklin (Acc. 42473), 2004 (Box 2)
- Campbell Avenue Historic District - 118 Campbell Dr., Roanoke (Acc. 37305), 1996; 2000 (Box 2)
- Campbell Farm, Shenandoah County (Acc. 45157), 1989 (Box 2)
- Campbell House, Rappahannock County (Acc. 44477), 2007 Nov 29 (Box 9)
- Cannon Branch Fort, Manassas (Acc. 39119), 2000 (Box 2)
- Cannon Branch Fort Site, Manassas (Acc. 45052), 2001 Aug 27 (Box 10)
- Cappahosic, Gloucester County (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 2)
- Carlton, Stafford County (Acc. 29886), 1973 (Box 2)
- Carrs-Brook, Albemarle County (Acc. 35187), 1982 (Box 2)
- Carter House, Carroll County (Acc. 44477), 2008 May 28 (Box 9)
- Carter-Mayo House - 205 W. Franklin St., Richmond City (Acc. 29886), 1977 (Box 2)
- Cedar-Crest, Boydton, Mecklenburg County (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 2)
- Centre Hill, Petersburg (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 2)
- Chancellorsville West Tract - Chancellorsville Battlefield, Spotsylvania County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Oct 8 (Box 10)
- Chapel Hill, Augusta County (Acc. 35680), 1996 (Box 2)
- Cherry Walk, Essex County (Acc. 35188), 1994 (Box 2)
- Chilton Property, Lancaster County (Acc. 44477), 2007 Aug 15 (Box 9)
- Chimney's, The, Fredericksburg (Acc. 29907), 1974 (Box 2)
- Christ Church, Lancaster County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 2)
- Citizen's Bank Building, Bedford (Acc. 35680), 1997 (Box 2)
- Clarendon School, Arlington County (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 2)
- Claughton-Wright House, Northumberland County (Acc. 44477), 2009 Jan 7 (Box 9)
- Cleydael, King George County (Acc. 44477), 2009 Jan 7 (Box 9)
- Clifton, Rockbridge County (Acc. 42473), 2004 (Box 2)
- Clifton Property, Northumberland County (Acc. 44477) 2007 Sept 27 (Box 9)
- Cobble Hill, Staunton (Acc. 42473), 2004; 2005 (Box 2)
- Cole Diggs House - 204 W. Franklin St., Richmond City (Acc. 29886), 1978 (Box 2)
- Columbia, Richmond City (Acc. 35187), 1978 (Box 2)
- Columbia Walker Tract, King William County (Acc. 29886), 1974 (Box 7)
- Conway - Moncure House, Falmouth, Stafford County (Acc. 42473), 2004 (Box 2)
- Cool Well, Hanover County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Jan 24 (Box 9)
- Cooley Farm, Goldie Hudson Tract - Cedar Creek Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 44477), 2008 May 9 (Box 9)
- Corotoman, Lancaster County (Acc. 29886), 1989 (Box 2)
- Craik House (Dr. James Craik House), Alexandria (Acc. 45157), 1991; 1992 (Box 2)
- Currier Farm / Rappahannock Station Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Nov 25 (Box 9)
- Daniel-Hardy House, Farmville (Acc. 45157), 1992 (Box 2)
- Davison Farm / Bowman's Mill Ford / Cedar Creek Battlefield, Warren County (Acc. 45052), 2010 May 5 (Box 10)
- DeJarnette's Tavern, Halifax County (Acc. 44477), 2007 Aug 29 (Box 9)
- Diehl Farm - Corss Keys Battlefield, Rockingham County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Dec 30 (Box 10)
- Dodona Manor, Leesburg, Loudoun County (Acc. 35680), 1997 (Box 2)
- Dover Slave Quarter - Brookview Farm, Goochland County (Acc. 41222), 2001 (Box 2)
- Dr. Tucker House, Buckingham County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Nov 9 (Box 9)
- Driver Tract - McDowell Battlefield, Highland County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Dec 4 (Box 10)
- Dulany-Joynt House, Alexandria (Acc. 32920), 1986 (Box 2)
- Dunn Farm - Trevilian Station Battlefield, Louisa County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Aug 7 (Box 9)
- Easton House (Isaac Eaton House), Loudoun County (Acc. 45157), 1989 (Box 2)
- Edge Hill, Caroline County (Acc. 35187), 1982 (Box 2)
- Edinburg Mill, Shenandoah County (Acc. 37305), 2000 (Box 2)
- Edmondson Hall, Washington County (Acc. 44477), 2009 June 4 (Box 9)
- Elk Hill, Bedford County (Acc. 35187), 1985 (Box 2)
- Elm Hill, Mecklenburg County (Acc. 33628), 1989 (Box 2)
- Elsing Green, King William County (Acc. 31008), 1980 (Box 2)
- Ely Mound Site, Lee County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 2)
- Enders Warehouse (John Enders Warehouse) - Shockoe Valley-Tobacco Row Historic District, Richmond City (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 2)
- Endview, Newport News (Acc. 44477), 2009 Mar 11 (Box 9)
- Erin, Warren County (Acc. 45157), 1997 (Box 2)
- Eyre Hill, Northampton County (Acc. 45157), 1990 (Box 2)
- Fairfax House (George William Fairfax House), Alexandria (Acc. 30654), 1979 (Box 3)
- Fairfield, Henrico County (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 3)
- Fall Hill, Fredericksburg (Acc. 29886 and 32920), 1973; 1980 (Box 3)
- Fan Area Historic District - 1100 Grove Ave. and 204 N. Harrison St., Richmond City (Acc. 41222), 2003 (Box 3)
- Fan Area Historic District - 206 N. Harrison St., Richmond City (Acc. 41222), 2003 (Box 3)
- Farm (The Farm), Charlottesville (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 3)
- Farmer's Bank, Petersburg (Acc. 45052), 2009 July 2 (Box 10)
- Farmer's Delight, Loudoun County (Acc. 35680), 1991 (Box 3)
- Farnley, Clarke County and Warren County (Acc. 33628 and 37305), 1989; 1999 (Box 3)
- Federal Hill, Fredericksburg (Acc. 41222), 2003 (Box 3)
- Ferrell Building, Danville (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 3)
- First Day Chancellorsville Battlefield, Spotsylvania County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 3)
- Fleetwood Heights - Brandy Station Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 44477), 2005 May 2 (Box 9)
- Fort Colvin, Frederick County (Acc. 43430) 2007 (Box 3)
- Fort Colvin, Frederick County (Acc. 44477), 2007 Aug 23 (Box 9)
- Fort Stover, Page County (Acc. 44477), 2007 Dec 28 (Box 9)
- Fort Vause, Montgomery County (Acc. 33628), 1989 (Box 3)
- Four Mile Tree, Surry County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 3)
- Fowle-Pickens House, Alexandria (Acc. 45157), 1987 (Box 3)
- Franklin and Armfield Office, Alexandria (Acc. 44477), 2009 Mar 11 (Box 9)
- Frascati, Orange County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 3)
- Frederick County Courthouse (Old Frederick County Courthouse), Winchester (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 3)
- Gay Mont, Caroline County (Acc. 29886), 1972 (Box 3)
- Gay Street Pasture - Washington Historic District, Rappahannock County (Acc. 37305), 1998 (Box 3)
- George Head House - Leesburg Historical District, Loudoun County (Acc. 45052) 2009 Nov 3 (Box 10)
- Glass Mill, Frederick County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Dec 9 (Box 9)
- Glen Burnie, Fluvana County (Acc. 39119 and 41222), 2000; 2002 (Box 3)
- Glencairn, Essex County (Acc. 37305), 2000 (Box 3)
- Glencoe, Radford (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 3)
- Gloucester Woman's Club, Gloucester County (Acc. 29886), 1975 (Box 3)
- Gordon House, Lynchburg (Acc. 45157), 1991 (Box 3)
- Grapeland, Northampton County (Acc. 30802), 1978; 1991 (Box 3)
- Gravel Hill, Charoltte County (Acc. 44477) 2007 Nov 5 (Box 10)
- Grayson County Courthouse, Grayson County (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 3)
- Green Falls, Caroline County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 3)
- Greenway Court, Clarke County (Acc. 41222), 2004 (Box 3)
- Greenwood, Orange County (Acc. 45157), 1993 (Box 3)
- Greystone - Waterford, Loudoun County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Sept 24 (Box 9)
- Groah Tract - Port Republic Battlefield, Rockingham County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Dec 16 (Box 10)
- Grove Mount, Richmond County (Acc. 45157), 1991 (Box 3)
- Gunnell House (William Gunnell House), Fairfax County (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 3)
- Gwaltney House (P.D. Gwaltney, Jr. House) - Smithfield Historic District, Isle of Wight County (Acc. 37305), 1998 (Box 3)
- Gyory Property - Brandy Station Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Nov 13 (Box 10)
- Hall, Virginius, King George County (Acc. 35187), 1993 (Box 3)
- Hallsboro Store, Chesterfield County (Acc. 42473), 2005 (Box 3)
- Hancock House, Richmond City (Acc. 45157), 1990 (Box 3)
- Hanger Mill, Augusta County (Acc. 43430), 2007 (Box 3)
- Hanover Tavern - Barksdale Theater, Hanover County (Acc. 45157), 1987 (Box 3)
- Harmony Hall - Fort Bowman, Shenandoah County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 3)
- Hillside - Waterford Historic District, Loudoun County (Acc. 45052) 1996 Apr 30 (Box 10)
- Hoffman Round Barn at Gentry Farm, Madison County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Sep 16 (Box 10)
- Hope Dawn, Bedford County (Acc. 45157), 1991 (Box 3)
- Hopkins and Bros. Store in Onancock, Accomack County (Acc. 42473), 2004 (Box 3)
- Hopkins Candy Factory, Mananssas (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 3)
- Hunter Property, Lynchburg (Acc. 45157), 1991 (Box 3)
- Huntsberry Tract - Third Winchester Battlefield, Frederick County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Aug 5 (Box 10)
- Hurstville and Cress Field, Northumberland County (Acc. 44477), 2009 Apr 24 (Box 9)
- Inge Tract - Appomattox Courthouse Battlefield, Appomattox County (Acc. 44477), 2009 Mar 5 (Box 9)
- Ingles Ferry Farm, Pulaski County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Aug 18 (Box 10)
- Ingles Ferry Farm, Pulaski County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Sept 17 (Box 10)
- Institute Farm, Loudoun County (Acc. 45157), 1991 (Box 3)
- Jackson Ward Historic District - 523 N. 1st St., Richmond City (Acc. 41222), 2001 (Box 4)
- Jackson Ward Historic District - 527 1st St., Richmond City (Acc. 41222), 2003 (Box 4)
- Jackson Ward Historic District - First Battalion Armory, Richmond City (Acc. 41222), 2003 (Box 4)
- Jackson Ward Historic District - Southern Aid and Life Building, Richmond City (Acc. 41222), 2003 (Box 4)
- Janelia, Loudoun County (Acc. 41222), 2003 (Box 4)
- Jefferson Street - 215, Alexandria (Acc. 45157), 1991 (Box 4)
- John Carlyle House, Alexandria (Acc. 44477), 2008 July 18 (Box 9)
- John Trone House - Buckland Historic District, Prince William County (Acc. 45052), 2009 July 29 (Box 10)
- Johnson House (Andrew Johnson House), Pearisburg, Giles County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 4)
- Johnston House (Zachariah Johnston House), Rockbridge County (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 4)
- Josephine School, Clarke County (Acc. 45157), 2002 (Box 4)
- Joynes House (Susan V. Joynes House) - 209 W. Franklin St., Richmond City (Acc. 29886), 1977 (Box 4)
- Keister House, Blacksburg, Montgomery County (Acc. 41222), 2001 (Box 4)
- Kelly's Ford Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 43430), 2007 (Box 4)
- Kemper Mansion, Madison County (Acc. 45157), 1989 (Box 4)
- Kenmore Woods, Spotsylvania County (Acc. 45052), 2008 May 1 (Box 10)
- Kennedy-Lunsford Farm, Rockbridge County (Acc. 37305), 1998 (Box 4)
- Kent-Valentine House, Richmond City (Acc. 29886), 1972 (Box 4)
- King and Queen County Courthouse Tavern, King and Queen County (Acc. 39119), 2000 (Box 4)
- Klugel Building (H.T. Klugel Building), Emporia, Greensville County (Acc. 35187), 1985 (Box 4)
- Kurtz Building - Winchester Historic District, Winchester (Acc. 41222), 2001 (Box 4)
- Lady Olivia at North Cliff Farm - Brandy Station Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 45052), 2010 June 21 (Box 10)
- Lee Hall, Newport News (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 4)
- Lee-Fendall House (and Garden), Alexandria (Acc. 37305 and 42473), 1999; 2005 (Box 4)
- Leslie Property - Aldie Battlefield, Loudoun County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Dec 22 (Box 9)
- Level Loop, Rockbridge County (Acc. 43430), 1993; 2006 (Box 4)
- Level Loop Farm, Rockbridge County (Acc. 45052), 2006 July 13 (Box 10)
- Lewis Store (Fielding Lewis Store), Fredericksburg (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 4)
- Lilly Tract at Bogota Farm - Port Republic Battlefield, Rockingham County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Nov 17 (Box 10)
- Lincoln Theater, Marion, Smyth County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 4)
- Linden Farm, Richmond County (Acc. 37305), 2000 (Box 4)
- Lloyd House, Alexandria (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 4)
- Lock-Keeper's House, Goochland County (Acc. 33628), 1988 (Box 4)
- Locust Grove, Culpeper County (Acc. 45157), 1991 (Box 4)
- Locust Hill, Madison County (Acc. 42473), 2005 (Box 4)
- Long Building (Edgar Long Building at Christiansburg Institute), Montgomery County (Acc. 43430), 2005 (Box 4)
- Long Meadow, Frederick County (Acc. 43430), 2005; 2007 (Box 4)
- Louis Pound Tract - Brandy Station Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Dec 31 (Box 9)
- Lower Bremo, Fluvanna County (Acc. 45157), 1980 (Box 4)
- Lowland Cottage, Gloucester County (Acc. 29886 and 43430), 1971; 2006 (Box 4)
- Lowland Cottage, Gloucester County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Jan 17 (Box 9)
- Lynnhaven House, Virginia Beach (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 4)
- Madden's Tavern, Culpeper County (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 4)
- Magruder Civil War Redoubt, Newport News (Acc. 33628), 1987 (Box 4)
- Main Street Station, Suffolk (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 4)
- Mansion House, Highland County (Acc. 45052), 2010 May 6 (Box 10)
- Marmion, King George County, 2008 Dec 22 (Acc. 44477), 2008 Dec 22 (Box 9)
- Marshall-Rucker-Smith House, Charlottesville (Acc. 39119), 2000 (Box 4)
- Mason House, Accomack County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 4)
- Mason-Dorton School, Russell County (Acc. 44477), 2009 May 26 (Box 9)
- Maury Place, Richmond City (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 4)
- Mayfield, Dinwiddie County (Acc. 29886), 1972 (Box 4)
- Mayfield Fortification Site, Manassas (Acc. 45052), 2001 Aug 27 (Box 10)
- Mayfield Fortification Site, Manassas (Acc. 39119), 2000 (Box 4)
- Meadows, The, Washington, Rappahannock County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 4)
- Melrose, Fluvanna County (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 4)
- Menokin, Richmond County (Acc. 35680), 1997 (Box 4)
- Menokin Core Area, Richmond County (Acc. 44477), 2008 Nov 13 (Box 9)
- Midway, Albemarle County (Acc. 33628), 1989 (Box 4)
- Molina Tract - Deep Bottom II Battlefield, Henrico County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Oct 14 (Box 10)
- Monterey - Kegley Property, Roanoke (Acc. 44477), 2007 Nov 5 (Box 9)
- Montpelier - Civil War Encampents, Orange County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Aug 21 (Box 10)
- Montpelier - Gilmore Cabin, Orange County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Aug 21 (Box 10)
- Monumental Church, Richmond City (Acc. 42473), 2004 (Box 4)
- Morven, Cumberland County (Acc. 45157), 1993 (Box 4)
- Moss Neck Manor, Caroline County (Acc. 37305 and 43430), 1998; 1999; 2005 (Box 4)
- Moton High School, Farmville, Prince Edward County (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 4)
- Mount Columbia, King William County (Acc. 33628), 1988 (Box 4)
- Mount Dumplin - Brandy Station Battlefield, Culpeper County (Acc. 45052), 2010 June 11 (Box 10)
- Mount Fair, Albemarle County (Acc. 37305), 1994 (Box 4)
- Mount Moriah Baptist Church, Roanoke (Acc. 41222), 2004 (Box 4)
- Mount Olivet Church, Petersburg (Acc. 45157), 1993 (Box 4)
- Mount Pleasant, Westmoreland County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 4)
- Mount Zion Old School Baptist Church, Loudoun County (Acc. 41222), 2002 (Box 4)
- Much Haddam, Loudoun County (Acc. 45157), 1990 (Box 4)
- Muddy Creek Mill, Cumberland County (Acc. 33628), 1989 (Box 4)
- Mulberry Hill, Lexington, Rockbridge County (Acc. 45157), 1982 (Box 4)
- Muster Grounds and Retirement, Abingdon, Washington County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Oct 8 (Box 10)
- Nanzatico, King George County (Acc. 29886), 1972 (Box 4)
- Oak Grove, Northampton County (Acc. 35680), 1993; 1994 (Box 5)
- Oakley Farm, Bath County (Acc. 43430), 2007 (Box 5)
- Oakley Hill, Hanover County (Acc. 35101 and 41222), 1996; 2001 (Box 5)
- Old Brick House - Conjuror's Neck Archaeological District, Colonial Heights (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 5)
- Old Dinwiddie Courthouse, Dinwiddie County (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 5)
- Old Mansion, Caroline County (Acc. 29886), 1969 (Box 5)
- Old Prince Edward County Clerk's Office, Prince Edward County (Acc. 37305), 1998 (Box 5)
- Old (Fifth) Prince William County Courthouse, Manassas (Acc. 37305), 1999 (Box 5)
- Old Rectory, Bedford County (Acc. 43430), 2006 (Box 5)
- Old Tobacco Warehouse, Urbanna, Middlesex County (Acc. 35680), 1997 (Box 5)
- Old Tobacco Warehouse, Middlesex County (Acc. 45052), 2009 Aug 16 (Box 10)
- Old Turner Place (King's Grant One), Henry County and Franklin County (Acc. 41222), 2004 (Box 5)
- Oregon Hill Historic District - 614-616 Albemarle St., Richmond City (Acc. 35680), 1996 (Box 5)
- Oregon Hill Historic District - 130 S. Cherry St., Richmond City (Acc. 39119), 2001 (Box 5)
- Oregon Hill Historic District - 615 S. Cherry St., Richmond City (Acc. 37305), 1998 (Box 5)